Hello and welcome to the second video of the NLN beginner course.
안녕하세요! n8n 초보자 강좌 두 번째 영상에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
Today we will be talking about APIs and webhooks, two very important notions that
오늘은 API와 웹훅에 대해 이야기해 볼 건데요, n8n 워크플로우를 만들기 전에 꼭 알아야 할 아주 중요한 개념들이에요.
you need to understand before building your first NLN workflows.
이번 영상에서는 API가 뭔지, 정의와 주요 구성 요소에 대한 설명을 드릴 거고요.
In this video we will be covering what an API is as well as a definition and an
그리고 '리버스 API'라고도 불리는 웹훅에 대해서도 알아볼 거예요.
explanation of its main components and we will be
자, 그럼 먼저 API가 뭔지부터 알아볼까요?
talking about webhooks sometimes called reverse APIs.
웹훅 (reverse API)에 대해서도 이야기할 거예요.
So, first of all what is an API?
우선, API가 뭘까요?
I'd like to start by explaining an analogy that is going to be very useful for
이해를 돕기 위해 비유를 들어 설명해 드릴게요. 이 비유는 API가 뭔지뿐만 아니라
understanding not only what an API is, but also
API의 여러 부분과 관련 용어를 이해하는 데 아주 유용할 거예요.
the different parts and names associated to them.
자, 식당에 앉아 있다고 상상해 보세요. 테이블에 앉아서
So, imagine you're sitting at a restaurant, and you go and you sit at a table.
어떻게 음식을 주문하죠? 음식을 어떻게 받나요?
How do you get food?
네, 웨이터에게 요청하죠.
Well, you ask a waiter.
그러면 웨이터는 여러분에게 또 다른 질문을 할 거예요.
question that he on the困 We are going to take your order and bring it to the kitchen.
주문받은 음식을 주방에 전달하겠죠.
Once the kitchen is done preparing your food, the
주방에서 음식이 다 준비되면,
waiter will bring back your food to the table.
웨이터가 다시 여러분의 테이블로 음식을 가져다줄 거예요.
This is very, very similar to how an API works.
이 과정이 API가 작동하는 방식과 아주 유사해요.
We're going to be using this analogy to explain the different parts of an API.
API의 여러 부분을 설명할 때 이 비유를 사용할 거니까 잘 기억해 두세요.
So keep this in mind while we go through this video.
그럼 이 비유를 염두에 두면서 영상을 시청해 주세요.
A technical definition of an API.
API의 기술적인 정의를 알아볼까요?
So an API is an application programming interface.
API는 '애플리케이션 프로그래밍 인터페이스'의 약자입니다.
It exposes a service and developers write programs to consume it.
API는 서비스를 제공하고, 개발자는 프로그램을 작성하여 이 서비스를 이용합니다.
So if we go back and we think of the actions or the apps in the past video,
지난 영상에서 봤던 액션이나 앱을 예로 들어볼게요. 구글 시트를 예로 들어볼까요?
we might take the example of Google Sheets.
구글 시트는 API를 가지고 있습니다.
So Google Sheets has an API.
그리고 API 안에는 여러 서비스가 있죠.
And in the API, we have an API.
예를 들어 API 안에서,
We have different services.
서비스가 있죠.
So one of these services might be get all of the data in a specific sheet.
이 서비스 중 하나는 특정 시트의 모든 데이터를 가져오는 것일 수 있습니다.
And so the Google Sheets API exposes the service
구글 시트 API는 시트의 데이터를
that allows you to read data in the sheet.
읽을 수 있는 서비스를 제공합니다.
Developers write programs to consume it.
그리고 개발자들은 이 서비스를 사용하기 위해 프로그램을 작성합니다.
So using NNN, we're going to be able to consume
n8n을 사용하면 구글 시트 API의
the Google Sheets API using the different services.
여러 서비스를 활용하여 데이터를 가져올 수 있죠.
For example, updating rows or getting data in a sheet.
예를 들어, 행을 업데이트하거나 시트의 데이터를 가져오는 것과 같은 기능을 사용할 수 있습니다.
Using this metaphor, we can see that the waiter
비유를 다시 보면, 웨이터는
is what's going to be called the interface.
'인터페이스'라고 부를 수 있어요.
And the application is going to be the kitchen.
그리고 '애플리케이션'은 주방이 되는 거죠.
So in this case, the application might be the Google Sheets.
이 경우, 애플리케이션은 구글 시트가 될 수 있습니다.
And then we're going to be using the interface to interact with the application.
우리는 인터페이스를 사용하여 애플리케이션과 상호작용하게 됩니다.
Why do we need this interface to interact with the application?
왜 애플리케이션과 상호작용하기 위해 인터페이스가 필요할까요?
Well, it allows us to abstract the complexity.
복잡성을 추상화할 수 있기 때문입니다.
Imagine if every time you went to a restaurant, instead of just sitting down
식당에 갈 때마다 그냥 앉아서 주문하는 대신
and ordering food, you had to go to the kitchen and explain your order,
주방에 가서 직접 주문을 설명하고, 음식이 다 될 때까지 기다렸다가
wait for it to be done, and then take your food back to your table.
직접 음식을 테이블로 가져와야 한다고 상상해 보세요.
This would be much more complicated than just asking the waiter for your food.
훨씬 복잡하겠죠? 그냥 웨이터에게 주문하는 것보다 훨씬 불편할 거예요.
The same thing goes for applications.
애플리케이션도 마찬가지입니다.
If every time you wanted to read data in a Google Sheet, you had to go to Google
구글 시트에서 데이터를 읽을 때마다 구글 서버에 직접 접속해서
servers, find your specific sheet, and then read the data from it,
특정 시트를 찾고, 거기서 데이터를 직접 읽어야 한다면
that would be much more complicated than just using the API, which gives you a very
훨씬 복잡하겠죠? API를 사용하면 데이터를 훨씬 추상화해서
abstract but easy way to access the data from the application.
애플리케이션의 데이터에 쉽게 접근할 수 있습니다.
So how does an API work?
그렇다면 API는 어떻게 작동할까요?
It uses what's called documentation.
API는 '문서'를 사용합니다. 문서요.
Documentation explains how the application programming interface or API works.
문서는 API, 즉 애플리케이션 프로그래밍 인터페이스가 어떻게 작동하는지 설명합니다.
And using the restaurant analogy in this case would be the menu.
식당 비유로 말하면, 이 문서는 메뉴판이 되는 겁니다.
So a little bit of terminology.
몇 가지 용어를 정리해 볼게요.
We send a request through the interface to the application,
우리는 인터페이스를 통해 애플리케이션에 '요청'을 보내고,
and the application uses the interface to send a response.
애플리케이션은 인터페이스를 통해 '응답'을 보냅니다.
We also have the client-server notions.
'클라이언트'와 '서버'라는 용어도 있어요.
In this case, you would be the client, and the
여기서 여러분은 클라이언트가 되고,
application and the interface would be the server.
애플리케이션과 인터페이스는 서버가 됩니다.
So keep these in mind when you see these terms.
이 용어들을 사용할 때 참고해 주세요.
When using APIs, we have, as mentioned earlier, requests and response.
API를 사용할 때는 앞서 말했듯이 '요청'과 '응답'이 있습니다.
So we're going to break down the different components of
이제 요청의 구성 요소와 응답의 구성 요소를
the request and the different components of a response.
자세히 살펴볼 거예요.
Starting with a request.
먼저 요청부터 살펴볼까요?
There are four main components to an HTTP request.
HTTP 요청에는 네 가지 주요 구성 요소가 있습니다.
In these videos, we're only going to be talking about HTTP requests.
이 영상에서는 HTTP 요청에 대해서만 이야기할 거예요.
There are different frameworks to make API requests, such as GraphQL.
GraphQL과 같이 API 요청을 만드는 데 사용되는 다양한 프레임워크가 있지만,
But most of the APIs that you're going to use are going to use the HTTP framework.
대부분의 API는 HTTP 프레임워크를 사용합니다.
Everything that we're going to talk about today is mirrored in the HTTP request node.
오늘 우리가 이야기하는 모든 내용은 HTTP 요청 노드에 반영되어 있습니다.
The HTTP request node allows you to make HTTP requests.
HTTP 요청 노드를 사용하면 HTTP 요청을 할 수 있습니다.
You can make HTTP requests in NNN and receive the responses.
n8n에서 HTTP 요청을 하고 응답을 받을 수 있습니다.
This is going to be very useful when building
이는 특정 API를 사용해야 하는 자동화를
automations that need to use specific APIs.
구축할 때 매우 유용할 거예요.
There are four components to an HTTP request.
HTTP 요청에는 네 가지 구성 요소가 있다고 했죠?
There is the URL, the method, the header, and the body.
URL, 메서드, 헤더, 그리고 본문이 있습니다.
Let's look at each one of them.
하나씩 살펴볼까요?
The URL is the unique location for a resource on the web.
URL은 웹상의 리소스의 고유한 위치입니다.
This can be a page, an image, a PDF, or some data.
페이지, 이미지, PDF, 또는 데이터가 될 수 있습니다.
Here we have an example of a URL.
URL의 예를 하나 보여드릴게요.
You can see a scheme, a host, a port, a path, and some query parameters.
스키마, 호스트, 포트, 경로, 그리고 쿼리 매개변수가 있죠.
The scheme, the host, and the path are going to be mandatory.
스키마, 호스트, 경로는 필수 요소이고,
And the port and query parameters are going to be optional.
포트와 쿼리 매개변수는 선택 사항입니다.
Something that is important to note, query
쿼리 매개변수는 항상 물음표로
parameters are always preceded by a question Mark.
시작한다는 것을 알아두세요.
Then we have the method.
다음은 메서드입니다.
The method describes the action that we want to perform.
메서드는 지정된 URL에서 수행하려는 동작을 설명합니다.
We want to perform at the given URL.
주어진 URL에서 수행하려는 작업입니다.
There are two main methods that we are going to be using for HTTP requests.
HTTP 요청에 사용할 주요 메서드는 두 가지입니다.
There is the GET and the POST methods.
GET 메서드와 POST 메서드가 있습니다.
GET, most of the time, allows us to receive information.
GET 메서드는 대부분 정보를 받는 데 사용됩니다.
So if you are reading data in a Google Sheet, you are using the GET method.
구글 시트에서 데이터를 읽을 때는 GET 메서드를 사용하는 거죠.
And POST is going to allow us to send information.
그리고 POST 메서드는 정보를 보내는 데 사용됩니다.
So if we want to send information from a form submission,
예를 들어 폼 제출에서 정보를 보내려면
we are going to be using the POST HTTP method.
POST HTTP 메서드를 사용해야 합니다.
The other methods are a little bit more rare.
다른 메서드들은 조금 더 드물게 사용됩니다.
We have, for example, DELETE, PUT, and PATCH, that are less common but can be used.
DELETE, PUT, PATCH와 같은 메서드가 있지만, 자주 사용되지는 않습니다.
What's very interesting with the method is there are all the time verbs, which means
메서드에서 흥미로운 점은 항상 동사라는 것입니다. 즉, 우리가 무엇을 하려고 하는지
that they describe very clearly what we are trying to do.
매우 명확하게 설명해 준다는 거죠.
So when wondering which method you need to use, think of which verb would be most
어떤 메서드를 사용해야 할지 고민될 때는 어떤 동사가 여러분이 하려는 작업에 가장 적절할지 생각해 보세요.
appropriate to the action you are trying to accomplish.
하려는 작업에 가장 어울리는 동사를 생각하면 됩니다.
Then we have the HEADER.
다음은 헤더입니다.
The header gives us a little bit more detail or context for a given request.
헤더는 주어진 요청에 대한 세부 정보나 컨텍스트를 제공합니다.
So, for example, common information that you will find in a header is going to be
헤더에서 흔히 볼 수 있는 정보는 여러분의 위치, 언어 설정, 장치 유형 등이 있습니다.
your location, or your language preference, or your device type.
여러분들의 위치, 선호하는 언어, 장치 유형 같은 것이죠.
Every time you open a page on the Internet, you are making an API request to
인터넷에서 페이지를 열 때마다 API 요청을 서버로 보내고,
a server, and the server is responding with the web page.
서버는 웹 페이지로 응답합니다.
So if you are browsing the Internet on your computer or on your laptop,
만약 여러분이 컴퓨터나 노트북에서 인터넷을 사용하고 있다면,
you are going to have different information or context in the header of your request.
요청 헤더에 서로 다른 정보나 컨텍스트가 포함될 거예요.
An example of a header would be ACCEPT APPLICATION JSON,
헤더의 예로는 'Accept: application/json'이 있습니다.
which tells the server that it would like the request.
이것은 서버에 요청과
And the response of the HTTP request in the JSON format.
HTTP 요청의 응답을 JSON 형식으로 받고 싶다는 의미를 전달합니다.
Then we have the BODY.
마지막으로 본문이 있습니다.
The BODY is optional and only exists for POST requests.
본문은 선택 사항이며, POST 요청에만 존재합니다.
It contains the information we would like to send to the server or application.
본문은 서버나 애플리케이션에 보내고 싶은 정보를 담고 있습니다.
So if we take the example of FORM SUBMISSION, then the BODY might contain
폼 제출의 예를 들면, 본문에는 '이름: Maxim', '성: POLSON',
first name Maxim, last name POLSON, and then the associated email.
그리고 관련 이메일과 같은 정보가 들어 있을 수 있습니다.
So this is the information that we are sending to the server.
이것이 우리가 서버로 보내는 정보입니다.
Finally, we have CREDENTIALS.
마지막으로 자격 증명(credentials)이 있습니다.
So the credential wasn't listed as a main part of
자격 증명은 HTTP 요청의 주요 부분으로
the HTTP request because it isn't a part on its own.
나열되지는 않았지만, 그 자체로도 아주 중요합니다.
There are many different ways to use credentials.
자격 증명을 사용하는 방법은 다양합니다.
A credential is how we let the application know
자격 증명은 우리가 특정 요청을 할 수 있는 권한이 있는지
that we are allowed to make a given request.
애플리케이션에 알려주는 방법입니다.
As you can imagine, if anyone could read your Google Sheets or update your Google
만약 누구나 여러분의 구글 시트를 읽거나 업데이트하거나, 슬랙에서 메시지를 보낼 수 있다면, 매우 위험하겠죠?
Sheets or send messages on Slack, that would be very dangerous.
위험하겠죠?
So we include credentials in our HTTP requests to indicate
그래서 우리는 HTTP 요청에 자격 증명을 포함시켜
to the server I am authorized to make this request.
서버에 이 요청을 할 권한이 있다는 것을 알려줍니다.
Most APIs require authentication through credentials.
대부분의 API는 자격 증명을 통한 인증을 요구합니다.
However, there are some APIs that do not require authentication.
하지만 일부 API는 인증을 요구하지 않기도 합니다.
The two most common ways to authenticate to a service are going to be through query
서비스를 인증하는 가장 일반적인 두 가지 방법은 쿼리 매개변수를 통한 인증과
parameters question Mark API key equals followed
'API 키=XXXX' 형식으로 API 키를 전달하거나,
by the API key or header authentication.
헤더 인증을 사용하는 것입니다.
For example, authorization colon bearer followed by the API key.
예를 들어 'Authorization: Bearer XXXX'와 같이 API 키를 전달하는 것입니다.
Another very common way to authenticate to a service is through OAuth.
서비스를 인증하는 또 다른 매우 일반적인 방법은 OAuth를 통하는 것입니다.
Every time you click sign in with Google and the little window opens and you sign
'Google로 로그인' 버튼을 클릭할 때 작은 창이 열리고 구글 계정으로 로그인하는 것이 바로 OAuth 인증 방식입니다.
in with your Google account, this is an OAuth authentication method.
작은 창이 열리면서 구글 계정으로 로그인하는 것이 OAuth 인증 방식입니다.
Now we've seen everything that we need to send a request.
이제 요청을 보내는 데 필요한 모든 것을 살펴봤습니다.
Now we're going to look at how the application is going to answer with a response.
이제 애플리케이션이 응답하는 방식을 알아볼 차례입니다.
There are three main components to an HTTP response.
HTTP 응답에는 세 가지 주요 구성 요소가 있습니다.
The status code, the header and the body.
상태 코드, 헤더, 그리고 본문입니다.
The status code is a three digit number which will give you information on whether
상태 코드는 요청이 성공했는지, 실패했는지에 대한 정보를 제공하는 세 자리 숫자입니다.
the request was successful or unsuccessful.
요청이 성공했는지, 실패했는지에 대한 정보를 알려줍니다.
The most common status codes are going to be 200, which means OK.
가장 일반적인 상태 코드는 200(OK)입니다.
This is the standard successful response.
이는 표준적인 성공 응답입니다.
It means your API request was executed well and the application is telling you
이는 API 요청이 성공적으로 실행되었으며 애플리케이션이
congrats, you did a good request.
성공적인 요청이었다고 알려주는 것입니다.
401, which means unauthorized.
401은 '인증 실패'를 의미합니다.
This is usually an authentication problem.
일반적으로 인증에 문제가 있을 때 나타납니다.
This is the application telling you the request that you sent me does not contain
애플리케이션은 보낸 요청에 이 요청을 수행하는 데 필요한
the authentication information necessary to make this request.
인증 정보가 포함되어 있지 않다고 알려주는 것입니다.
This means you need to go back and check your credentials and
이 경우에는 자격 증명을 확인하고
how you sent them or the access that your credentials have.
자격 증명을 어떻게 보냈는지, 또는 자격 증명에 어떤 권한이 있는지 확인해야 합니다.
Another one is 404.
또 다른 상태 코드는 404입니다.
You might remember this from the web.
웹에서 본 적이 있을 거예요.
Not found.
'Not Found'입니다.
Usually this is a problem with the URL and means that the page or data you are
URL에 문제가 있다는 뜻이며, 찾고 있는 페이지 또는 데이터가 지정한 URL에 없다는 의미입니다.
looking for is not on the URL that you indicated.
요청한 URL에는 데이터가 없다는 의미입니다.
Finally, we have 500, which is internal server
마지막으로 500은 '내부 서버 오류'를 의미합니다.
error, which indicates that the server had an error.
서버에 오류가 발생했다는 것을 나타냅니다.
This means it was not your fault, but the server's fault.
이는 여러분의 잘못이 아니라 서버의 잘못이라는 의미입니다.
In general, the very easy way to remember and understand these codes, if the status
일반적으로 이 코드를 쉽게 기억하고 이해하는 방법은 상태 코드가 2로 시작하면, 성공적인 HTTP 요청이라는 뜻입니다.
code starts with a 2, congrats, it was a successful HTTP request.
축하해요! 성공적인 HTTP 요청입니다.
If it starts with a 4, you made some kind of
4로 시작하면 여러분이 어떤
error and you need to modify your request.
실수를 했고 요청을 수정해야 한다는 의미입니다.
500 means it was the server's error.
500은 서버 오류를 의미합니다.
Most of the time it just means try again later.
대부분의 경우 나중에 다시 시도하라는 의미입니다.
Then, the same way we included a header in the request, the application is going to
요청에 헤더를 포함시킨 것과 마찬가지로, 애플리케이션도 응답에 헤더를 보내서
send a header in the response, giving more context or detail.
더 많은 컨텍스트나 세부 정보를 제공합니다.
Some common response headers are going to be how long is the content, how much
일반적인 응답 헤더는 콘텐츠 길이, 응답에 포함된 콘텐츠의 양,
content is in the response, what type of
콘텐츠 유형 또는
content is it, or when does this content expire.
콘텐츠 만료 시점 등이 있습니다.
How long am I going to have access to it for?
얼마나 오랫동안 이 콘텐츠에 액세스할 수 있는지 알려주는 것이죠.
Finally, sometimes we're going to have a body.
마지막으로 본문이 있을 수 있습니다.
The body is the actual data being returned.
본문은 실제로 반환되는 데이터를 말합니다.
It can be in many different formats.
다양한 형식일 수 있습니다.
It can be HTML if we're browsing the web.
웹을 탐색하는 경우 HTML일 수 있고,
It can be JSON or it can be any other forms of data.
JSON일 수도 있고, 다른 형태의 데이터일 수도 있습니다.
For example, binary data.
예를 들어 바이너리 데이터 같은 것이요.
Then, let's quickly talk about webhooks or reverse APIs.
자, 그럼 웹훅 또는 리버스 API에 대해 빠르게 이야기해 볼까요?
Imagine you're at home waiting for some friends.
집에서 친구들을 기다리고 있다고 상상해 보세요.
You can either go and check the door every few minutes to see
몇 분마다 문을 확인해서 친구들이 왔는지 볼 수도 있고,
if they've arrived, or you can wait for the doorbell to ring.
초인종이 울릴 때까지 기다릴 수도 있습니다.
The doorbell in this analogy is a webhook.
여기서 초인종이 바로 웹훅입니다.
It is what indicates that something that you are waiting for happened.
웹훅은 여러분이 기다리고 있는 일이 일어났다는 것을 알려줍니다.
So, let's say you're using Stripe.
스트라이프를 사용한다고 가정해 봅시다.
Stripe is a developer platform to manage payments.
스트라이프는 결제를 관리하는 개발자 플랫폼입니다.
And you need to know every time a new payment is made in your Stripe account.
스트라이프 계정에서 새로운 결제가 이루어질 때마다 알고 싶다고 가정해 봅시다.
Well, there are two options.
두 가지 옵션이 있습니다.
Either we can do what is called polling.
하나는 '폴링'이라고 하는 것입니다.
So, every few minutes, for example, we can make a new request to Stripe.
예를 들어 몇 분마다 스트라이프에 새로운 요청을 보내서
A new API request saying, is there a new payment?
새로운 결제가 있는지 확인하는 API 요청을 보내는 거죠.
If yes, do some actions.
만약 새로운 결제가 있다면, 어떤 작업을 수행하고,
If no, wait.
없다면 기다립니다.
And every few minutes, keep asking and keep polling
그리고 몇 분마다 스트라이프에
the Stripe application to see if we have a new payment.
새로운 결제가 있는지 계속 물어보는 겁니다.
Or we can set up a webhook.
또는 웹훅을 설정할 수도 있습니다.
And every time that a new payment is made in Stripe, a webhook is going to be sent
스트라이프에서 새로운 결제가 발생할 때마다 웹훅이 즉시 전송되어
to us synchronously, giving us the information on the payment.
결제 정보를 실시간으로 받아볼 수 있는 거죠.
So, every time we're waiting for something to happen, or we're waiting for
우리가 어떤 일이 발생하기를 기다리거나, 특정 애플리케이션 또는 서비스로부터
information from a specific application or service, sometimes
정보를 기다릴 때, 때로는 이러한 애플리케이션에서
these applications are going to allow us to create webhooks.
웹훅을 만들 수 있도록 허용합니다.
What we need to set up a webhook is a URL.
웹훅을 설정하려면 URL이 필요합니다.
What is the location we are sending the information to?
정보를 보낼 위치가 어디인지를 지정해야 하는 거죠.
And then we can use a tool like n8n and the webhook node to receive and manage and
그런 다음 n8n이나 웹훅 노드와 같은 도구를 사용하여 이 정보를 수신 및 관리하고
deal with this information, triggering a workflow.
워크플로우를 트리거할 수 있습니다.
That was it for the second video of this beginner course on APIs and webhooks.
API와 웹훅에 대한 초보자 과정의 두 번째 영상은 여기까지입니다.
In the next video, we will be covering n8n nodes and everything
다음 영상에서는 n8n 노드와 첫 번째 워크플로우를
you need to know to start building your first workflows.
구축하기 위해 알아야 할 모든 것을 다룰 거예요.
See you in the next video.
다음 영상에서 만나요!